Finding Aid for Michigan Library Association records
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Library Association records
1891-1991
Michigan Library Association
45 linear feet
851867 Bz 2
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records of the Michigan Library Association were first transferred to the Bentley Library in 1941, with several accessions thereafter (Donor no. 1514 )
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The collection is open for use without restriction.
The Michigan Library Association (MLA) was founded in Detroit on September 1, 1891, for the purpose of promoting the cause of librarianship throughout the state. Today the Michigan Library Association's membership includes librarians, library trustees, and library friends groups. For each year since 1891, members of the Michigan Library Association have gathered at their annual conference to discuss and debate topics of concern to Michigan librarians. To further inform their members, the MLA publishes a quarterly journal, The Michigan Librarian.
MLA is closely related to the American Library Association and supports its interest in libraries and library professionals. In addition, MLA cooperates with regional library and state professional organizations, such as the Midwest Federation of Library Services, the Michigan Association for Media in Education, the Adult Education Association, and the State Library of Michigan.
Other activities of the MLA derive from the various sections that make up the organization. The association is composed of seven districts that meet annually to discuss regional issues. The MLA is divided into sections which are called divisions, caucuses, and committees. Divisions are composed of members who wish to promote library service and librarianship within a particular type of library activity. Caucuses are composed of members who wish to promote library service and librarianship and who share the same interest. There are two types of committees within the MLA, operational and activity.
As of 1988, the MLA had 5 divisions, 14 caucuses, 8 operational committees, and 3 activity committees. The divisions at that time were: Academic and Research Library, Children's Services, Friends, Trustees, and Public Library. The 14 caucuses were: Bibliographic Instruction, Community Colleges, Cooperatives, Junior Members Roundtable, Library Education, Management and Administrative, Marketing and Public Relations, Media, Preservation, Reference, Rural Libraries, Specialized Services, Technical Services, Young Adults. The operational committees consisted of: Awards and Resolutions, Conference, Conference Program, Constitution and Bylaws, Editorial Board, Headquarters and Finance, Membership and Promotion, and Nominations. The activities committees were: Continuing Education and Professional Standards, Intellectual Freedom, and Public Policy. These groups do not always keep the same title. For example, they may change from committee to caucus or division.
Pre-1990 Accessions (boxes 1-36)
1990 accession (boxes 37-44)
1993 Accession, 1977-1991 (box 45)
The pre-1990 accessions from the Michigan Library Association (MLA) are available in three broad groups of material which overlap one another in terms of office of origin, dates, and subjects. This arrangement reflects the way the material was received from the MLA.
The papers received with the 1990 accession cover the years 1937-1952 and 1961-1989 with the bulk of the material from 1980-1989.
The papers received in 1993 cover the years 1977-1991 and mostly contain records of the Intellectual Freedom Committee. Accession also includes bylaws, minutes of the Management and Administration Forum, policies and procedures, and minutes of the Executive board, 1981-1983.
Subjects:
Libraries--Michigan.; Michigan Library Association.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Libraries--Michigan.; Michigan Library Association.
Genre Terms:
Motion pictures.; Photographs.; Television broadcasting--United States.; Videotapes.
- Correspondence, 1905-1964
  The first nine feet (boxes 1-9) consist of five feet of correspondence and other papers arranged chronologically (1905-1964), and four feet of unarranged financial reports, scrapbooks, membership lists, and miscellaneous association records.
  - 1905-1941 (Box 1)
  - 1942-1944 (Box 2)
  - 1944-1948 (Box 3)
  - 1949-1956 (Box 4)
  - 1957-1964 (Box 5)
- Financial reports
  - 1908 (Box 6)
  - 1930s-1960s (Box 6)
  - membership lists (Box 6)
    (unarranged)
- Scrapbooks; reports
  - Scrapbooks; reports (Box 7)
- Miscellanea
  - 1940s (Box 8)
  - 1940s (Box 9)
    cont.
- Executive Board, 1915-1968
  The second nine feet of material (boxes 10-18) dates from 1915 to 1969, while the third group (boxes 19-36) dates from 1891 to 1982. The organization of these two groups of material follows the organizational structure of the association. Within the organization records are divided by type of material (such as minutes, reports, correspondence, etc.) and then chronologically.
  The organizational structure of the MLA contains eleven types of bodies. The Executive Board is made up of elected officers and two members-at-large. Executive Board records consists of minutes and correspondence dealing with association business. Correspondence of the executive secretary and the president is also found with these records.
  - Minutes, 1929-1968
    - 1929-1936 (Box 10)
    - 1937-1942 (Box 10)
    - 1943-1949 (Box 10)
    - 1950-1953 (Box 10)
    - 1954-1959 (Box 10)
    - 1960-1964 (Box 10)
    - 1965-1968 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1915; 1924-1968
    - 1915, 1924; 1926-1927 (Box 10)
    - 1930-1939 (Box 10)
    - 1940-1949 (Box 10)
    - 1950-1959 (Box 10)
    - 1960 (Box 10)
    - 1961 (Box 10)
    - 1962 (Box 10)
    - 1963 (Box 10)
    - 1964 (Box 10)
    - 1965 (Box 10)
    - 1966 (Box 10)
    - 1967 (Box 10)
    - 1968 (Box 10)
  - Vice-president Correspondence (Box 10)
    - 1962-1964 (Box 10)
  - Executive Secretary Correspondence
    - 1953 (Box 10)
    - 1956 (Box 10)
    - 1959-1960 (Box 10)
    - 1963-1967 (Box 10)
  - Financial
    - Statements and budgets
      - 1932 (Box 11)
      - 1940-1942 (Box 11)
      - 1946-1953 (Box 11)
      - 1957 (Box 11)
      - 1959 (Box 11)
      - 1961 (Box 11)
    - Correspondence
      - 1953-1954, 1966-1967 (Box 11)
- ALA Councilor
  - Reports (Box 11)
- Divisions, 1948-1968
  Divisions are created either by grouping together similar types of libraries or by grouping together individual librarians who perform similar functions. For most divisions, there are minutes, reports, correspondence, and other materials that record the division's activities. The School Library Division is among the more fully documented, including records regarding its annual fall and spring institutes, and special programs.
  - Academic (College)
    - Minutes/Reports, 1960-1966; 1956; 1958 (Box 11)
    - Correspondence, 1964-1966 (Box 11)
    - Special Committee-Cooperative Library Service to Extension Students
      - Correspondence, 1965; 1960 (Box 11)
  - Friends
    - Minutes/Reports, 1960-1962 (Box 11)
    - Correspondence, 1963; 1967 (Box 11)
  - School Libraries Division-School and Children's Library
    - Annual reports, 1952-1966; 1968 (Box 11)
    - Annual Committee reports, 1951-1955; 1958 (Box 11)
    - Minutes, 1951-1963; 1967 (Box 11)
    - Correspondence
      - 1934, 1938 (Box 11)
      - 1952-1959, 1948-1949 (Box 11)
      - 1960-1963 (Box 11)
      - 1964-1966 (Box 11)
      - 1967-1968 (Box 11)
    - Committees
      - Booklist
        - Correspondence
          - 1951 (Box 11)
          - 1956-1958 (Box 11)
          - 1963 (Box 11)
          - 1965 (Box 11)
        - Booklists (Box 11)
      - Conference Committee, 1958 (Box 11)
      - Constitution Committee
        - Correspondence
          - 1957 (Box 11)
          - 1962 (Box 11)
          - 1964-1965 (Box 11)
        - Constitutions (Box 11)
      - Coordinating Committee on School Libraries
        - 1952 (Box 11)
        - 1948-1950 (Box 11)
      - Committee on Education for Library Work with Children in School and Public Libraries, 1956; 1954 (Box 11)
      - Evaluation Committee, 1955-1956; 1959-1962 (Box 11)
      - Institute Study Committee, 1963 (Box 11)
      - Joint Committee for the Development of School Libraries
        - Correspondence
          - 1959-1961 (Box 11)
          - 1963-1964 (Box 11)
      - Michigan Authors and Illustrators Committee
        - 1959-1962 (Box 11)
        - 1965 (Box 11)
        - 1968 (Box 11)
      - Name, Function and Membership Committee, 1962 (Box 11)
      - Nominating Committee, 1957; 1959; 1961; 1964 (Box 11)
      - Public Library Service to Children
        - 1950-1951 (Box 11)
        - 1961-1963 (Box 11)
        - 1965-1968 (Box 11)
      - Public Relations
        - 1951 (Box 11)
        - 1962 (Box 11)
        - 1965 (Box 11)
      - Publications-Michigan Librarian (Box 11)
      - Recruitment, 1951 (Box 11)
      - Standards, 1951 (Box 11)
    - Spring Institutes
      - 1952-1963 (Box 11)
      - 1965-1966 (Box 11)
    - Fall Institutes
      - 1962-1967, 1954 (Box 11)
      - 1968 (Box 11)
    - MLA Conference, 1965 (Box 11)
    - Center State Institutes
      (Teacher-Librarian Institute)
      - 1946 (Box 11)
      - 1948 (Box 11)
      - 1951 (Box 11)
      - 1953-1954 (Box 11)
      - 1958-1963 (Box 11)
    - Michigan Association of School Librarians
      - 1960-1962 (Box 11)
    - Teacher Certification Code, 1957 (Box 11)
    - White House Conference on Children, 1960 (Box 11)
    - State Executive Board of School Librarians
      - 1940-1944 (Box 11)
    - Student Library Assistants Association of Michigan
      - 1952 (Box 11)
      - 1957 (Box 11)
      - 1959-1964 (Box 11)
    - Financial
      - Budgets and Statements, 1954-1964 (Box 11)
    - Membership Lists (Box 11)
  - Trustees
    - Minutes/Reports
      - 1941-1958 (Box 11)
      - 1959-1961, 1964 (Box 11)
      - 1966-1967 (Box 11)
    - Correspondence
      - 1938-1952 (Box 12)
      - 1953-1959 (Box 12)
      - 1960-196l, 1964-1967 (Box 12)
    - Committee of 50, 1963-1964 (Box 12)
    - ALA Trustee Citation Committee
      - 1963 (Box 12)
      - 1966 (Box 12)
    - Newsletter, 1959 (Box 12)
    - Manuals of Procedure for District Chairman of the Trustee Division (Box 12)
    - Financial
      - 1952-1953 (Box 12)
      - 1955-1957 (Box 12)
    - Membership Lists (Box 12)
- Sections, 1937-1968
  Sections, sometimes called roundtables, deal with specific topics of library service, such as adult education, the Cooperative Caucus, or the reference. Minutes, correspondence, and other material makes up the bulk of the section records.
  - Adult Education
    - Minutes/Reports
      - 1940 (Box 12)
      - 1942 (Box 12)
      - 1945 (Box 12)
      - 1947 (Box 12)
      - 1952-1955 (Box 12)
      - 1959-1961 (Box 12)
      - 1964-1965 (Box 12)
    - Correspondence
      - 1941-1942 (Box 12)
      - 1956-1961 (Box 12)
      - 1962-1966 (Box 12)
    - Community College
      - Annual reports
        - 1964-1965 (Box 12)
    - County and Regional
      - Minutes/Reports
        - 1959, 1961-1962 (Box 12)
      - Correspondence
        - 1949 (Box 12)
        - 1956 (Box 12)
        - 1958-1959 (Box 12)
        - 1961-1963 (Box 12)
    - Federal Relations
      - Reports
        - 1945-1947 (Box 12)
        - 1953 (Box 12)
    - Group Relations
      - Reports/Correspondence
        - 1938-1941 (Box 12)
    - Hospital and Institutional Libraries
      - Reports/Correspondence
        - 1956 (Box 12)
        - 1960-1961 (Box 12)
        - 1965 (Box 12)
        - 1967 (Box 12)
    - Junior Members
      (Newcomers)
      - Minutes/Reports
        - 1940 (Box 12)
        - 1944-1947 (Box 12)
        - 1950-1951 (Box 12)
        - 1956-1959 (Box 12)
        - 1961-1963 (Box 12)
      - Correspondence
        - 1939 (Box 12)
        - 1945 (Box 12)
        - 1948 (Box 12)
        - 1955-1966 (Box 12)
        - 1967 (Box 12)
    - Library Administration
      - Reports/Correspondence
        - 1960-1961 (Box 12)
        - 1964-1965 (Box 12)
        - 1967 (Box 12)
    - Library Development
      - Correspondence
        - 1954 (Box 12)
    - Library Laws
      - Correspondence
        - 1958-1961 (Box 12)
    - Media
      (Audio-Visual)
      - Correspondence
        - 1952 (Box 12)
        - 1961 (Box 12)
        - 1965 (Box 12)
    - Reference
      - Minutes/Reports
        - 1936 (Box 12)
        - 1961 (Box 12)
        - 1964-1965 (Box 12)
      - Correspondence
        - 1947 (Box 12)
        - 1952-1961 (Box 12)
    - Relations with Publishers
      - Minutes/Reports
        - 1951-1953, 1955 (Box 12)
    - Technical Services
      - Minutes/Reports
        - 1954-1962 (Box 12)
        - 1964, 1966 (Box 12)
      - Correspondence
        - 1954-1956 (Box 12)
        - 1966-1968 (Box 12)
      - Cost Accounting Study
        - 1961-1962 (Box 12)
      - Membership Lists (Box 12)
- Activities Committees, 1932-1968
  Activities committees deal with issues relevant to all types of libraries and library professionals. For example, the Intellectual Freedom committee offers support to local libraries dealing with censorship issues and the Legislative committee coordinates the lobbying activities of the association.
  - Intellectual Freedom Committee
    - Minutes/Reports (Box 13)
      - 1952-1956, 1959 (Box 13)
      - 1961 (Box 13)
    - Correspondence
      - 1954-1955 (Box 13)
      - 1960-1961, 1963; 1966-1967 (Box 13)
    - Manual for Action (Box 13)
  - Legislative Committee
    - Minutes/Reports
      - 1932-1936 (Box 13)
      - 1940, 1942 (Box 13)
      - 1950, 1951; 1953; 1954; 1955; 1958-1959 (Box 13)
      - 1961 (Box 13)
    - Correspondence
      - 1936, 1940-1941; 1949 (Box 13)
      - 1950-1951, 1957-1959 (Box 13)
      - 1960-1961, 1963-1964; 1966-1967 (Box 13)
    - Newsletters
      - 1954-1960 (Box 13)
      - 1962 (Box 13)
      - 1967 (Box 13)
    - Subcommittees
      - Re-codification of Library Laws (Box 13)
      - State Library Boards and Commissions (Box 13)
  - Public Relations
    - Minutes and Reports, 1951; 1962 (Box 13)
    - Correspondence
      - 1953, 1958-1960 (Box 13)
      - 1961-1962 (Box 13)
      - 1963-1964 (Box 13)
      - 1965-1967 (Box 13)
    - Brochure Project, 1961-1963 (Box 13)
    - Answers to Promotion Inquiry, 1964 (Box 13)
    - Penal Fines, 1957-1959 (Box 13)
    - National Library Week
      - Correspondence
        - 1955 (Box 13)
        - 1957 (Box 13)
        - 1959-1961 (Box 13)
        - 1966-1967 (Box 13)
      - Handbook for Procedures, 1960 (Box 13)
  - Salary Survey: Personnel Policies
    (Salary, Staff and Tenure)
    - Minutes/Reports
      - 1942, 1944 (Box 13)
      - 1950-1953 (Box 13)
      - 1961-1965 (Box 13)
    - Correspondence
      - 1941, 1944 (Box 13)
      - 1951 (Box 13)
      - 1963, 1966-1967 (Box 13)
    - Subcommittee-Pensions-1950) (Box 13)
- Operations Committee, 1908-1969
  Operation committees perform the housekeeping chores of the association. The Conference committee files contain programs of and reports regarding the association's annual conference. The Recruitment and Scholarship committee's records reflect a time when there was a severe shortage of trained, library professionals.
  - Awards
    - Librarian of the Year Award Committee
      - Correspondence, 1967 (Box 14)
    - Loleta D. Fyan Award Committee
      - Correspondence, 1963; 1966-1967 (Box 14)
  - Conference
    - Programs, 1930; 1932-1936; 1946-1947 (Box 14)
    - Handbook of Procedures (Box 14)
    - Conferences
      - Reports of Annual Meeting
        - l908 (Box 14)
        - 1921-1922 (Box 14)
        - 1923-1924 (Box 14)
        - 1925 (Box 14)
        - 1926 (Box 14)
        - 1927 (Box 14)
        - 1928 (Box 14)
        - 1934 (Box 14)
        - 1936 (Box 14)
        - 1947-1951 (Box 14)
        - 1966-1967 (Box 14)
      - Correspondence
        - 1942, 1946; 1950-1951 (Box 14)
        - 1952 (Box 14)
        - 1954-1955 (Box 14)
        - 1956 (Box 14)
        - 1957 (Box 14)
        - 1958 (Box 14)
        - 1959 (Box 14)
        - 1960 (Box 14)
        - 1961, 1963 (Box 14)
        - 1964 (Box 14)
        - 1965 (Box 14)
        - 1966 (Box 14)
        - 1967 (Box 14)
        - 1968-1969 (Box 14)
      - Exhibits Committee
        - 1955, 1957; 1960-1961 (Box 14)
    - Constitution and Bylaws
      - Minutes/Reports
        - 1951, 1953; 1961-1963 (Box 14)
      - Correspondence
        - 1941, 1945-1946 (Box 14)
        - 1959-1963, 1964-1967 (Box 14)
      - Constitutions MLA's Sections (Box 14)
  - History
    - Correspondence-1963, 1966 (Box 14)
  - Institutes and In-Service Training
    - Correspondence
      - 1941, 1946 (Box 14)
      - 1951-1952 (Box 14)
    - Subcommittee on Teacher Training
      - 1941-1944, 1947; 1949 (Box 14)
  - Membership
    - Minutes/Reports
      - 1952-1954 (Box 14)
      - 1960-1961, 1964-1965 (Box 14)
    - Correspondence
      - 1941, 1945 (Box 14)
      - 1963, 1966-1967 (Box 14)
    - Honorary Membership Committee, 1964 (Box 14)
  - Nominations and Elections
    - Correspondence
      - 1944-1945, 1947 (Box 15)
      - 1953-1954, 1956; 1958-1959 (Box 15)
      - 1961-1963, 1966; 1968 (Box 15)
  - Planning
    - Minutes/Reports
      - 1935-1939 (Box 15)
      - 1941-1942, 1944-1946; 1948 (Box 15)
      - 1950-1957, 1959-1963 (Box 15)
      - 1965-1966 (Box 15)
    - Correspondence
      - 1938-1941 (Box 15)
      - 1960-1961, 1963; 1965-1968 (Box 15)
    - Subcommittee
      - Correspondence-1946 (Box 15)
  - Publications
    - Minutes/Reports
      - 1951, 1953-1954 (Box 15)
      - 1961-1962 (Box 15)
    - Correspondence
      - 1944-1945 (Box 15)
      - 1953 (Box 15)
      - 1963, 1966 (Box 15)
    - Subcommittees
      - Michigan Authors, 1944 (Box 15)
      - Michigan Librarian, 1945; 1949-1950; 1963-1965; 1969 (Box 15)
  - Recruitment and Scholarship
    - Minutes/Reports,,,, 19651966, 1943-1947; 1949; 1950-1959; 1961 (Box 15)
    - Correspondence
      - Recruitment
        - 1948-1949 (Box 15)
        - 1950-1957 (Box 15)
        - 1960-1963 (Box 15)
      - Scholarship
        - 1941, 1947-1950 (Box 15)
        - 1952-1954, 1956-1957; 1959 (Box 15)
        - 1964-1967 (Box 15)
    - Constance Bement Memorial Fund, 1954 (Box 15)
    - Inter-Association Scholarship Board
      - Correspondence, 1965-1966 (Box 15)
    - Flyers, Pamphlets, and Materials on Careers and Scholarships (Box 15)
  - Resolutions
    - Correspondence
      - 1941 (Box 15)
      - 1952, 1954 (Box 15)
- Districts, 1924-1967
  Districts represent librarians within a particular geographic area. District records document meetings and other activities which brought together librarians from a specific geographic area.
  - General
    - Roundtables
      - 1924, 1928; 1931; 1933; 1935-1938 (Box 16)
    - Programs, 1953; 1950; 1949 (Box 16)
    - Correspondence
      - 1939-1949 (Box 16)
      - 1950-1954 (Box 16)
      - 1955-1959 (Box 16)
      - 1960-1964 (Box 16)
      - 1965-1967 (Box 16)
    - Institute for Planning District Meetings, 1954 (Box 16)
    - Newsletters, 1954-1956 (Box 16)
    - Manuals of Procedures (Box 16)
    - Maps (Box 16)
  - District I
    - Correspondence
      - 1942-1947 (Box 16)
      - 1950, 1954-1956; 1959-1961 (Box 16)
      - 1964-1965 (Box 16)
  - District II
    - Correspondence
      - 1941-1943, 1945; 1947 (Box 16)
      - 1951-1955, 1957; 1958 (Box 16)
      - 1960-1961, 1965 (Box 16)
  - District III
    - Correspondence
      - 1942, 1944-1945; 1947 (Box 16)
      - 1950-1952, 1954 (Box 16)
      - 1961, 1964-1965 (Box 16)
  - District IV
    - Correspondence
      - 1939-1942 (Box 16)
      - 1945-1949 (Box 16)
      - 1951, 1954-1959 (Box 16)
      - 1961, 1965-1966 (Box 16)
  - District V
    - Correspondence
      - 1945, 1947 (Box 16)
      - 1951-1957, 1959 (Box 16)
      - 1965 (Box 16)
  - District VI
    - Correspondence
      - 1939-1940 (Box 16)
      - 1945, 1947 (Box 16)
      - 1954, 1956; 1959 (Box 16)
      - 1961, 1965-1967 (Box 16)
  - District VII
    - Correspondence
      - 1945, 1947 (Box 16)
      - 1952, 1955-1956 (Box 16)
      - 1960-1961, 1965 (Box 16)
- Related Library Groups/Associations
  Records regarding related library groups document the MLA's work with other associations and professional organizations, such as the American Library Association and the State Board for Libraries.
  - Michigan Council for Better Libraries (Box 17)
    - Correspondence, 1959-1961 (Box 17)
  - Michigan Council on Education
    - Correspondence, 1938-1940 (Box 17)
  - State Board for Libraries
    - Minutes
      - 1941-1942, 1945-1946; 1948-1965; 1967 (Box 17)
    - Correspondence
      - 1936, 1939-1941 (Box 17)
      - 1947 (Box 17)
      - 1951-1952, 1954; 1956-1957 (Box 17)
      - 1960, 1961-1963; 1964-1967 (Box 17)
    - Standards
      - 1953-1954, 1956-1958 (Box 17)
      - 1965 (Box 17)
    - Proposed Plan for Reorganization of Department of Education, 1965 (Box 17)
    - Library Services and Construction Act-Program, 1965 (Box 17)
  - American Library Association (Box 17)
  - Meeting of State Library Associations (Box 17)
- Workshops/Projects/Conferences
  The Workshop/Project files document specialized activities of the MLA. These activities include projects such as workshops dedicated to developing services for immigrant groups.
  - Conference on Financing Michigan Government (Box 17)
  - Correspondence-1940
    - Library Community Project (Box 17)
  - Correspondence-1955-1956
    - Governors Conference on Libraries (Box 17)
    - Correspondence-1962 (Box 17)
  - Peace and War Conference
    - Correspondence-1964 (Box 17)
  - 75th Anniversary Committee
    - Correspondence-1965 (Box 17)
  - Metropolitan Library Project
    - Correspondence-1966 (Box 17)
  - Conference Program Planning Institute1958 (Box 17)
- MLA Administrative Materials
  MLA administrative material includes manuals of procedures, committee descriptions, and checklists for incoming chairpersons.
  - Articles of Incorporation (Box 17)
  - Checklists (Box 17)
  - Committee Functions (Box 17)
- Committees, 1937-1967
  Temporary committees were formed to discuss special topics, such as the effect of the state constitutional convention of 1961 on library service.
  - Architectural Award Committee
    - Correspondence, 1966-1967 (Box 17)
  - Committee on Education for Library Service, 1944 (Box 17)
  - Advisory Committee
    - Correspondence, 1959 (Box 17)
  - Auditing Committee
    - Correspondence, 1947 (Box 17)
  - Special Committee on Finance
    - Correspondence, 1963 (Box 17)
  - Group Hospitalization
    - Correspondence, 1939-1941 (Box 17)
  - Lending Section Roundtable
    - Correspondence, 1935; 1938; 1941 (Box 17)
  - Special Committee to Study Library Laws
    - Correspondence, 1961 (Box 17)
  - Public Act 379
    - Correspondence, 1967 (Box 17)
  - Redistricting Committee
    - Correspondence, 1950 (Box 17)
  - Relations with State Government
    - Correspondence, 1936; 1939 (Box 17)
  - Statement of Belief Committee
    - Correspondence, 1954 (Box 17)
  - Special Joint Committee on State Aid Law
    - Correspondence, 1949-1950 (Box 17)
- Miscellaneous, 1914-1964
  Miscellaneous was the final category created to contain material that did not otherwise fit into the organizational scheme. These remaining files cover topics such as the use of penal fines to fund library programs.
  - Bibliographies and Assorted Speeches, 1914; 1915; 1924 (Box 18)
  - Interim Study, 1953 (Box 18)
  - Michigan State Library, 1935-1936 (Box 18)
  - Penal Fines, 1960; 1963-1964 (Box 18)
  - Public Library Development, 1953; 1959 (Box 18)
  - State Aid for Libraries, 1962 (Box 18)
  - State Wide Plan for Libraries
    - Correspondence, 1960-1964 (Box 18)
    - Printed Materials (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Materials (Box 18)